So, you just finished some in-depth work on a
6502 CPU emulator. Now, you might think that
the only reason we ever use CPU emulators are
for learning and they're great for learning,
right? So, I can give you a screen and it has
a program counter and a Z flag and an N flag
and instruction memory and you can go change the
instruction memory, you can start it, you can stop
it. It prints a lot of stuff out. You can hover
over an instruction and it shows you what the
instruction is and what the ASCII character might
be stored there etc etc etc and it keeps it really
simple so we can write pretty small programs. We
can also look at the emulator code itself and I've
got in the upper corner a URL that is the actual
machine code emulator that's running when you're
doing your assignments or just playing with it.
So if you go look at that it's JavaScript and you
you've learned JavaScript and it has to run in the
browser. So I have implemented a 6502 instruction
set in JavaScript in a browser. The core of this
is a function called execute step which should be
called like fetch execute cycle because what it
really does is it's going to run one instruction.
So which instruction is it going to run? Well,
you can see in that first line it's going to look
at this.cpu.pc the program counter. Where are the
instructions? Well, they're in an array. So we're
going to use the PC to look up the instruction in
the array. What's the instruction? It's an integer
from 0 through 255. It's a single eight-bit
number. And so the next thing it's going to do
is have a big long if then else with like 40 or 50
different instructions. The first instruction it
checks to see is if we got all zeros. Well, the
000000 instruction is the break, the halt. And
so what happens is the in the the emulator prints
the output from this from the data memory and then
it sets itself to not running. And then the fact
execute cycle stops. And there's a bunch more else
elsees. If it doesn't find an instruction that
it understands, it has one last else that blows
up and sets it to running equals false. You might
just go have some fun and see if you can figure
out a bit pattern that will cause the emulator to
blow up with an unknown instruction. And after we
processed one instruction, well, we advance
the program counter. It's what we do at the
fetch execute cycle. Now, if there was a jump, if
one of those instructions was a jump instruction,
it already changed the PC. Do you remember how
I told you that a jump instruction is kind of
like a load into the PC? It's almost like a load
immediate into the PC. So, that that code up in
the instruction processing sets the PC increment
to zero to indicate that it's already been changed
to a completely no new location by a jump.
So if the PC increment is greater than zero,
we simply say add the PC increment. That little
mask is there to make sure it doesn't get bigger
than 256 because there's only 256 instructions
in the instruction memory. And the PC increment
is going to either be one if it's an 8-bit
instruction or two if it's a 16- bit instruction.
Digging a little more deeply into some of those
else- if else if else if else ifs, you can see
the load accumulator immediate instruction.
It's a 0xa9. And what we do is we say, oh,
let's get that immediate value. Take that CPU
instructions and go one beyond the PC and grab
it. So that's the number that we're loading. And
all what do we do? Well, we take the immediate
value and we put it in the accumulator.
And every time you change the accumulator,
you got to update the Z and the N flag. So we
got a function to do that and then we say hey
this was a 16- bit instruction increment the PC by
two subtract immediate again we grab the immediate
which is the immediately following after the
program counter we compute the difference and then
we set the accumulator to be the difference update
the status flex because we changed the accumulator
and set the PC increment to two and we do like
something a little more complex which is a load
with an address and an offset by the X register.
Again, the base address is an immediate. So,
we go one beyond the the program counter and grab
that. Then, we grab the X register. Make sure it's
a number, not a string. That uh that's that's
probably just conservative programming. Then
we take the base address plus the X value. That's
our offsetting to our index by X. And then we go
grab the real memory. CPU.memory of the effective
address. what is memory is a 256 byte array and
then we set the accumulator to whatever came out
of that memory and we update the status flags and
we set the p increment to two. So again this is
about 1300 lines of code. I would not claim it's
a perfect emulator. I just did it well enough to
make it so that you can learn what you need to
learn in this class. Um, I would say probably
I could make it a lot more accurate if I made
it 2500 lines of code. If I did things like made
all the memory mapping for sound and stuff work,
it'd probably be three or four times larger, maybe
5,000 lines of code. That's not a lot of code.
The interesting thing is that most modern
processors on phones and computers are so fast
that even if we're writing something in JavaScript
that's emulating historical machine code, it can
do that far faster than the original hardware. So
if you build an emulator for a 6502 and you want
to do one megahertz, well, you probably will have
to slow it down. And things like graphics are way
better in modern environments and they they don't
take a lot of resources. So, if we go back to the
70s and the 80s, people would buy things like
Atari 2600s and play them on their televisions.
They would have these these plug-in ROM modules
that had the code in it. That's the machine code.
And so, there's an effort to capture these and
you can actually disassemble these. The ROMs
are things you can read with ROM readers and then
you can extract the machine code and then you can
build an emulator. And it turns out that the Atari
2600 is a has a 6502 in it. So the console that
you plugged into the Atari 2600, that machine code
is 6502 machine code. So you build an emulator,
including all the graphics capabilities of the
2600. And so you can emulate a game like Space
Invaders on the Atari 2600 in your browsers and
completely play it. I encourage you to go ahead
and play it. Um, if you slow down the startup
now, once things get cached in your browsers,
this screen goes by so fast you won't even see it.
I had to record it to catch it. You can see what's
going on as the game is being loaded. It's looking
at the files. It's the the the machine code for
the game and it's running it in the browser
using a piece of software written in WASM. Now,
it's not written in JavaScript. It's written in
WASM. What is WASM? WASM is web assembly. So I
built a machine language emulator in JavaScript
that you were using. But there is a low-level
high performance machine language emulator built
into web browsers, recent web browsers called web
assembly. So web assembly is a machine code
that is not intended to be built in hardware
but intended to be emulated very very rapidly
by hardware. So for a wide range of software,
you can do com surprisingly complex things and
then compile them to WASM, download them into
a browser and run them in a browser with a little
JavaScript library that provides things like file
opening etc etc. Now I want to show you a bit
of WASM. It's got a little bit different syntax
than most assembly languages but it still is
a very succinct one to one correspondence to
binary machine code. I will also show you in the
C programming for everybody course that I teach
at www.cc4e.com the C playground actually doesn't
run the code in the server. It compiles C to WASM
in the server and then runs WASM in the user's
browser. So you can't run an infinite loop in my
C programming for everybody course and break my
server. You can write an infinite loop and break
your browser but that is your browser. So let's
take a little bit of a look at web assembly. WASM
is a little bit different. So you don't see for
example an accumulator. It actually has a stack
and it has operands on the stack and it you put
operands on the stack and then you operate on the
operand ends of the stack and they replace things
on the stack. It's a very simple execution model.
Um but it's still very very low level and what
this is is this is printing hello world. You
see this sort of indentation. It it still is
machine code. If you look below, there's about
90 bytes of machine code that I dumped from this
particular uh bit of code compiled into WASM. It
uses a little different syntax because it really
doesn't want to expose labels in WASM. It really
wants there to be a stack. It wants to be a set of
nested like modules and variable scopes and things
like that. Um but still it's an assembly language
and it is got nesting. So, so you tend not to use
labels in the same way that we use labels in
more traditional assembly language and machine
language. And here is a simple example of a thing
you can just go to this website and play with
it. You can write CC code. You hit the run code
button. It uploads the CC code to a server which
then compiles it to WASM that takes very little
time and it downloads that WASM and then it runs
that WASM as output and shows the output of it.
That also means that in that WASM compiler for C,
there's a whole standard library includes
stdio.h and the printf that's been compiled
to WASM as well. So the WASM you get back from
incripum is much larger than a just a pure WASM
uh bit of code because it's compiled the C library
as well so that you can do things like print f and
scan f and other kinds of things that you would
do in a C application. So emulators going forward
are so fast and becoming ubiquitous that it's kind
of foolish to write native code for certain things
like video games and and other things. And so the
uh the fact that you're playing with an emulator
uh going forward in the future, you may be writing
code for production that runs in an emulator.